A Guide to the George Washington Estate Papers, 1784-1870
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
George Washington Estate Papers, 1784-1870
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7797-f-g
This collection consists of ca. 98 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased on August 2 and September 15, 1988.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 98 items, 1784-1870, chiefly autograph letters and documents pertaining to the settlement of the estate of George Washington and the business concerns of the Washington family. Most of the correspondence is addressed to Bushrod Washington and Lawrence Lewis, executors of George Washington's estate. Other letters and business papers are concerned with the Washington family, the Dismal Swamp Land Company, and Virginia politics.
Legal and financial papers consist of accounts, inventories, powers of attorney, rents due, receipts, deeds, and bills, and include: a list of the rents due General Washington by his tennants in Loudoun, Fauquier, and Berkeley Counties (1784-1785); an inventory of the sale of horses (1797); an account with the physicians, Dr. Dangerfield and Dr. Thornton (1813, 1814, & 1818); a military land grant to George Lewis (1821); the case of Michael Cresap vs. Archibald McClean (1823 Jul) and an estimate of the property belonging to the estate of George Washington unsold by the executors (ca. 1800). Also present is an autograph of George Washington Parke Custis (1857 Jul 13). A helpful reference work pertaining to this collection is The Estate of George Washington Deceased by Eugene E. Prussing.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- W. W. Lewis to L. Lewis 1801 Apr 17
  He furnishes a detailed report concerning the Kanawha lands belonging to George Washington located in Wood, Kanawha, and Ohio Counties [present-day West Virginia], including the Round Bottom and Burning Spring tracts. He asks whether Lewis wants him to continue renting the lands and to settle a dispute with Sheriff Alderson over his collection of back taxes on Washington's property. Lewis also describes the damage done to the Mill Creek Settlement by settlers who cut down the sugar trees, and mentions the controversy over the Kanawha lands with James Welch, who had leased some of the lands from Washington.
- Jonathan M. Herndon to [Lawrence Lewis] 1803 Feb 21
  He agrees to survey the twenty-three equal lots of the Kanawha area if Lewis will hire some men to lay off the lots at his own expense, and if Herndon will be paid regardless of any obstructions to prevent the survey, such as those made by Major James Welch.
- William Herndon to Lawrence Lewis 1803 Feb 22
  He makes further arrangements to provide companions to assist Jonathan Herndon in surveying Kanawha lands and asks that one of the legatees accompany him to the site.
- John Walker to [Bushrod Washington?] 1803 Aug 26
  Discusses the land which fell to his brother Francis Walker as their father's residuary legatee. Because he was the only acting executor Washington's letter was sent to him.
- Francis Walker to John Walker 1803 Sep 2
  Discusses three tracts of land in Nansemond County purchased in partnership for the purpose of cutting a canal from the lands of the Dismal Swamp Land Company to the Nansemond River. Although he was formerly authorized by General Washington and John Lewis (the representative of Col. Fielding Lewis) to dispose of the land at Suffolk, he was not able to get a good price. He had paid one third of all expenses on the land to Washington while in Philadelphia.
- Samuel Shepard to [Lawrence Lewis] 1804 Mar 5, Jun 30 & 1805 Feb 10
  Reports on the lands in Kanawha and Wood Counties belonging to the Washington family wrongfully returned for nonpayment of taxes by Sheriff Alderson of Kanawha County, and acknowledges receipt of payment of the taxes
- Thomas Lewis to [Bushrod Washington] 1804 Mar 11
  Suggests that Washington ask George Ball to pay at least a third payment of the remainder owed on the Washington land in Gloucester County sold to Ball in 1797
- William Fleming to Thomas H. Ellis 1804 Jun 16
  Recommendations of books to read in preparation for his law examination and eventual practice
- Noah Limby to Archibald McClean 1804 Jun 27
  Describes the particulars of the controversy over the Round Bottom tract, located on the east side of the Ohio River in Marshall County [West Virginia], ca. fifteen miles below Wheeling, which Washington sold to Archibald McLean in 1799, but did not convey before his death.
- Chapman Johnson to Col. James Breckinridge 1805 May 20
  Writes about his presentation of Breckinridge's petition to the Chancellor in Staunton Court, and his affection for Letitia [Breckinridge]
- Edward W. Tupper to [?] 1805 Nov 30
  Reports that he had forwarded 320 dollars to the Bank of the United States in Washington City to be paid to addressee on order, and that he had been in Gallipolis (on the Ohio River) trying to sell part of the owner's tract of land in the Northwest Territory. He had one offer from a Mr. Marshall who wanted one third of his section, paying either 320 dollars due next fall or in salt. He also believes that there may be considerable iron ore on the property.
- Chapman Johnson to Col. James Breckinridge 1805 Dec 13
  Reports that the Chancellors did not pronounce a decree in any of the cases mentioned in Breckinridge's memorandum, and on the progress of Crockett vs Floyd
- Francis Peyton to Bushrod Washington 1805
  Sends Washington a Power of Attorney to transact business for himself and encloses the mortgage for property he purchased in Alexandria for which he requests the deed
- John G. Ladd to Bushrod Washington 1806 Jun 26
  Asks for payment by the Estate for a 150 dollar debt
- Francis Peyton to Bushrod Washington 1806 Aug 19
  Reports that Shepard is unwilling to pay his debt until convenient to himself, offers to prosecute him for the entire debt and give Washington security for the repayment of the balance. Otherwise he requests the earliest possible payment from the Estate
- [Thomas?] Law to Dr. E[lisha]; C[ullen] Dick 1806 Oct 23
  Asks if Dick if willing to accept his plan for settling the claims he has against Dick
- Andrew Parks to [Bushrod Washington] 1807 Feb 18
  Writes concerning the settlement with Mr. Hoy of his debt for a city lot. He offers as security for the debt the deed of trust for his lands in Jefferson County, [West Virginia]
- Jonathan Robinson to Bushrod Washington 1807 Feb 22
  Sends a copy of the law requested by Washington and discusses the lands of General George Washington upon which taxes has not been regularly paid
- Andrew Parks to Col. William Augustine Washington 1807 Mar 6
  Asks what is the greatest amount of time that Mr. Hoy will allow for the payment of his debt, upon giving a deed of trust for his lands in Jefferson County, [West Virginia], with the powers of selling if he does not comply with the terms
- Elias Caldwell to Bushrod Washington 1807 Mar 16
  Informs Washington that Mr. Hoy will accept Andrew Parks deed of trust with the property to be sold if not paid in twelve months
- Elias Caldwell to Col. William A. Washington 1807 Mar 27
  Informs him of Hoy's terms delaying suit against Andrew Parks for twelve months
- Thomas Hammond to Bushrod Washington 1807 Jun 6
  Authorizes him to act as he thinks best in regard to the McClean land
- William Perrell to Bushrod Washington & Lawrence Lewis 1807 Sep 22
  Discusses the taxes due and rents paid on lands belonging to George Washington's Estate in Wood, Kanawha, and Mason Counties
- [James Henderson] to [Bushrod Washington] 1811 Jun 6
  Sends a draft for the dividend to the George Washington Estate from the Dismal Swamp Land Company
- Thomas Swepson to [Bushrod Washington] 1811 Jun 22
  Reports that he has exchanged the North Carolia notes for notes acceptable to the Bank of Norfolk and agrees to deposit the dividend from the Dismal Swamp Land Company in the bank for Washington
- James Henderson to [Bushrod Washington] 1812 Feb 12
  Requests his consent as a member of the Dismal Swamp Land Company to postpone the general meeting for one month to allow their agent time to get the juniper shingles to market and have enough funds to make the dividend equal to last years. He also reports the managers' purchase of an half share belonging to the estate of Col. John Jamieson and the subscription for five additional shares in the Dismal Swamp Canal Company
- Robert A. Taylor to [Bushrod Washington] 1812 Mar 28
  Relates the offer of Mr. Wright to purchase two Nansemond County land tracts equalling one hundred and twenty acres
- James Henderson to [Bushrod Washington] 1812 Jun 11
  Reports on the profits and progress of the Dismal Swamp Land Company and the resolution passed directing the President and managers to apply to the Legislature for an act authorizing the Company to sue and be sued in the name of the President and managers
- Robert Taylor to Bushrod Washington 1812 Sep 30
  Writes about the selling of his Nansemond lands
- James Henderson to Bushrod Washington 1817 May 25
  Sends him the managers' draft on their Treasurer at Norfolk for his Dismal Swamp Land Company dividend
- James Henderson to Bushrod Washington 1818 May 23
  Sends a draft for his Dismal Swamp Land Company dividend and discusses the erection of new flood gates and repairs to the Jericho mill
- John Thompson to [Lawrence Lewis] 1820 Mar 5
  Speaks of the scarcity of money and tells him that Mr. Wood will settle his account when he sees Lewis
- John N. Gibbons to Bushrod Washington 1820 Jul 17
  Encloses the other halves of the notes and sends them to Washington
- Bushrod Washington to Major Lewis 1821 [n.m.] 30
  Writes about the statement of Ransom's debt and the sale of "Rock Hall"
- John N. Gibbins to Bushrod Washington 1821 Dec 27
  Informs him that his draft was honored and the proceeds credited to his account with the Bank of the United States
- William A. Craig to Bushrod Washington 1822 Dec 21
  Writes about a debt due to John Leachmann from the George Washington Estate
- William Sewell to Bushrod Washington 1823 Feb 14
  Discusses a deed given to the heirs of Samuel W. Middleton of Charles County not yet executed by Washington's attorney
- Thom Williamson to Bushrod Washington 1823 Mar 7
  Informs Washington that he has received a check on the Bank of Virginia, payable in Carolina notes, and drawn by Fielding Lewis, President of the Dismal Swamp Land Company, which he converted into current funds and placed into Washington's account
- Fielding Lewis to Bushrod Washington 1823 Dec 1
  Sends his dividend from the Dismal Swamp Land Company for the year
- Archibald McClean to Bushrod Washington 1823 Dec 15
  Discusses his legal controversy with Michael Cresap and Mr. Tomlinson and asks that Mr. Wickham make the main draft of the answers to Tomlinson's suit
- Joseph C. Cabell to Dear Brother 1824 May 2
  Asks his brother to have the Resolutions of November 1814 copied out at the foot of the enclosed letter and to attach the two bank schemes and send them with an explanatory letter to William Wirt who is to give the whole to President Monroe. He also asks Cabell to explain to Col. Barbour and Col. Mercer that they had "overlooked these small resolutions."
- Robert Douthet to Bushrod Washington 1824 Aug 13
  Discusses the arrangement of securing an agent for Washington to receive his dividend from the Dismal Swamp Land Company and to represent him at the meetings. He also describes his plans for bringing in greater profit by expanding the canal system to reach more timber stands, abandoning the farming and milling operations, which had been operating at a loss, and concentrating on the production of shingles
- M. B. Barton to Bushrod Washington 1826 Jan 30
  Inquires about payment of his fee
- Mr. Brazer to Lawrence Lewis 1826 Mar 14
  Writes re the exchange of some of his trees for those from Mount Vernon, sends Mrs. Lewis a treatise on early education by Mrs. Hoare of London, and speaks of the "relicks of General Washington" and Mr. Lee's poetical heresies about Lord Byron and John Milton
- Jonathan Elliot to Lawrence Lewis 1826 Jul 17
  Asks Lewis to remit the four dollars due on the Washington Gazette for the period before its transferral to the Telegraph
- D. Sheffey to Bushrod Washington 1826 Aug 11
  Apologizes for the confusion over who he would represent in Mr. Andrews Parks case against Mr. Beverly
- [Warner Walker] to the Rev. William Meade [1826?] Oct 21
  Defends himself from rumors that he has "withdrawn from the sacrament, of which I never had an idea, having ever entertained the utmost veneration for that holy rite"
- E. T. Lee, Jr., to Bushrod Washington 1826 Oct 23
  Informs Washington concerning the case of Cresap vs. McClean that both Cresap's and Tomlinson's cases may be considered at an end in the court at Wheeling
- A.C. Cazenove and Company to George L. Lane 1827 Apr 27
  Writes about flour sold to Cazenove by Lawrence Lewis
- William Smith to Dear Sir 1827 Jul 6
  Writes concerning the transcript of proceedings in the case of the Washington legatees vs. the Washington executors
- William Bright to Lawrence Lewis 1828 Sep 27
  Discusses the payment by the United States Treasury to recompense him for his slave taken away by the British and the poor health of Mrs. Custis
- William Shepard to [Lawrence Lewis] 1834 Jun 6
  Discusses the taxes on the Nansemond lands of the George Washington Estate
- Col. Lewis W. Washington to Isaac S. Lyon 1870 Apr 29
  Informs Lyon that all of his letters of the Washington family are of a private nature and he hopes to make a selection from them for publication, after which he might furnish him with some autograph of a distinguished Southern gentleman